Hello, everyone good-morning how we are doing today.
Thank you so much for joining us my name is were...microsoft on the holland experiences team doing community
management we've got a wonderful...people that here to talk to-you about developing for
halloween's you know,...wanted to start...guys introduce yourself.
Hi, I'm jeff norris and I
lead the operations laboratory of the nasa jet propulsion lab.
I'm the project manager for the on-site application that has the system
...using to control rovers on mars using poland's people up.
First-time impressed from the coordinated appearance here where...gray thank you for like
...status...moi.
So, my name is...have a gore...the program manager for the
...project ...I'm a professor of radiology at the keys was reserve university.
I...sanders imus studio manager...our experiences team working on
...for microsoft's so we have kind of
...the n small teams that have been looking at what we think some of the end-user early
end-user experiences could...so these...people all have experience developing
...and something that I'm sure a lot of you may be interested in so we figured we bring them on stage to kind
of share those experiences with you guys been very active in communicating with us your questions and we've been collecting them for a
while but you do have the chance to send your questions to
us should you...have a few minutes for qa at the end if you want to do and I think the throw slide up
here soon enough the number to text your questions in is nine zero start your text
messes with the word build make sure to do that and then a space
...your question they will send it out on the
interest of time clearly there are a lot of people in this room we won't be able to get to all of them but again we've been
collecting we've been listening so we've got some kind of frequent questions that have been
...on the contact us page on holland dot com which
...start with so yep nine-zero start with build
send way we'll get to what we can jeff let's start with you were...or
...jpl with the first announced partnered
...developer talk...through a little bit of your experience early on like
what brought you here today thanks versus is really a pleasure to be here with all you guys
...a computer sinus developer and you know, been building systems for controlling
robots and spacecraft at gpl for about fifteen years what brought
us here really is that we are passionate about
enabling exploration and we already know a lot about expiration everyone knows a lot of
expiration because human beings are natural explorers we have these incredible
abilities to understand environment's just by being present
in those environment it's difficult then when we try to
explore distance environment's through traditional devices like a computer
screen and...and keyboard and things like that because these are really barriers to
our understanding these are things that
force our brains to very laboriously form models in our minds of these just
...on input that we
weren't evolved to deal with so for us the
journey that brings here is really a journey about expiration
and presence we see this technology as a
weighing for us to allow our scientists and engineers
to engage not only their natural abilities...humans but all the things that they've learned
...been educated on
...more effectively explore places like marsh andyou know,
we're really thrilled about is that this isn't just an idea or
a hunch for us which has been actually for a long-time it is a reality for us
and we'll be using this in mission operations for the curiosity...over the summer?
So, I know gps...on education and inspiring future
...feature sciences if you will talk us through a little bit of what you think
...be able to do for that assuming...I get
...passion about so we nasa's responsibility is not just to
explore its or first responsibility...also to share that journey with
everyone it's a human endeavour not just
...for a few nasa scientists and engineers so for us the potential
what we're doing here doesn't end with the scientists and engineers that are executing
...missions but with everyone I think all of us are
excited about inspired by, you know, you venture into
the unknown and this allows us to engage with the with everyone in a way that we really have been able to
...I mean we do our best right now to show people the data comes back
more missions to talk to people about it to go...the world and presentations about it but
here we have a technology where we can make it possible for people to be there with
us to be there with each other to see what we're doing and maybe even
to contribute to it in a way that we've just never had before
so for me it's about enabling the what
say is like the next apollo moment the next moment where, you know,
all of humanity can gather together and share in a moment
that so pivotal so important that it defines
...experience and are progress and expiration so of course you mention...being,
you know, new exciting technology new steps forward with that have to come certain challenges one
as you take us through couple challenges that you face...developing for...holographic computing
your choice...so instead of a developer so,
when we when we were starting out with our early steps with this platform
...surprising you guys
that was challenging the one thing I'll mention that comes to mind is that?
Well, my lab had a intervention that we had been working with
pr and ar technologies for many years and had built
up some experience however the area we were trying to apply this technology was
...area and we had some very new goals in our
minds new ambitions and I don't mind saying that like a lot of
our first instincts were wrong and that
your forma picture in your mind about...this is going to be great this is this,
you know, this menu or this wave interacting or this way of looking at things
going to be perfect and then you can sketched out a piece of paper you can, you know,
righted up and look at it on a computer screen and,
you know, feel great about it and then put it... to...reality and saywell,
you know, my intuition was wrong and on one hand
it's discouraging on the other hand it's what makes this so exciting for me personally as a developers
just that we have the opportunity here to train our intuition in a
completely new medium and we have to be patient with ourselves
what we do that but I gotta say that some of those first days those first ideas of like this is
...who that's terrible, you know, that was you know,
eight you know, a learning process that we had to go through does anyone else of any a challenge they like to share
...flowery, yeah, we...the ui designing and developing for the
...was definitely is a complete new
...it's everything and how we do it I think we redid...a few times of forced
...dev...out there he talked to be about...lot...very happy but, it
ways it was also awesome and that we could completely re imagine how
we interact with the technology itself so the accessibility for what you
could do by taking your real-world and your mixed world...real-world
...your digital world...of lying there's next to each other just opens up a whole new type of interface
and what you can you can experience with the user can experience and it's really
framing it's very it's a creative process so, to be able to get back
into space where you can kind of be real like sort-of inventors again because
...exist doesn't exist now no one's to find it there's no rules...things that
getting your way for how you might do it...you get to experiment a lot and then I think the biggest
pieces just learning to sort of fell fast pick up and then we've made a lot of progress
to so we've learned a lot we found some really great ways just the ability to use your user
...right like that that's really powerful and it's exciting?
I could add into that as well I think that it's this case you the our to do
completely new type of interaction not just with your digital world but,
among people and this gets to what jeff was talking about that you can and
it's really shown in the trimble world as well
that you could have multiple people sitting in the same room interacting with the
same digital object and this is you know,
this could be somebody who's with you in the room next to you or could be somebody
who's remote like in onsite demo...but yet it feels like they're next
to you and it's that person-to-person interaction that is why I'm here because
that's the only way you can educate I don't know-how I educate with you know,
a person it with the no-point screen in front of their
face I don't I can't have any idea what they're experiencing but,
this is just a very natural way to get people
to interact with digital things that may not exist yet and but we
still back to the challenge I still have no idea how-to-do-it the right way it's this
...wide open area because you can walk around things so,
you know, three-d you why I don't know what that looks like this is wide open?
I think that...a user experience is one of the most critical aspect of this technology and
it's a completely new paradigm content completely way to interact with the world and this was
romain chimes during the development of the solution we presented in the keno.
...ad may think eventually we'll reach the point where this kind of
development will have, you know, widget sets and ui standards install guides and things like that
which none of that exist today and I think part of the opportunity, you know, for
all of you and for us and...other people who are starting to work in this area is to like
...that grounded find out what is the right idea and you look at how other
media a when the emerged imitated the previous media and
...found their own...like that's what we're going to...
Maybe one note about this...above the user experience challenge and
...exploring ways to interact there was one version which had some
shadows.
On the on the reality so you have those object...cast shadows but then we did
assign study who is our tool...to check how the sun is, you know,
houses house reaction of our building design building
in specific hours-long today and I see...this shadow of the
...is moving with everything and this is of course something will not see
...the rely so you always try to figure out what the best way to provide
...user the way to interact without really mixing what you have there was a
real world.
Fovea you kind of just alluded to my next question for-you why don't you
explain a little bit about the announcement happen this week to work the troubles doing with
...and what you're working on your so triple is serving industry
like geospatial mining heavy civil and for this specific project
...building industry first I'm an architect real architect
not the system architect or moi?
And, we figure out that there...a tremendous
...for this industry because the construction industry is in a way
...strategy by definition you're dealing with digital content design content that the
...engineer and engineer provide and
construction side you need to figure out to mix them together in order to provide a more
efficient process and actually what we did is we
created a proof of concept which follows this process starting with an architect doing
his design work checking design
...using...and the
holographic in the context of the physical model so we can actually
see easy relations between his design and the environment in a much better
way and...satisfied with his resolve...start to share
...the real-world so the share...with others remotely
or in the office and everyone can work around kind of democratic sizing the
data like it I was not dictates you and I will decide where you will go
and see my model you can actually go around look everywhere it's
a fantastic way to analyze and explore and identify issues doing design
process and once this is done very challenging aspect of the work
today's to transfer this data from the office.
To the side.
And, just imagine yourself as a construction worker straining it's
called you need to open those twenty documents and try to understand where should I
puts the stuff whereas this column supposed to be
but if you can presented data in the context of the...is no need for
...so it's really great tool for us to
true improve the customers experience.
...this of...though anyone feel free to answer what was it like the first-time you experience tolerance
...thoughts what you think about the possibilities?
We came here and not here to redman to one of the early hall...academie.
And, that we had a bunch of developers with us one of them is
...the rights are actually.
And, in about two days we were able to publish.
Architecture...structural models into
...and the first-time I put a device and I was looking at the structure model for study
...it was it was fascinating it's really exciting moment and I remember when we
follow-up on the real work on the proof of concept
and noun the on the real product developing
we took an architect to work with us to really design staff
...we wanted to feel how it how is it for real...work on it and
...and it was specifically waiting for the moment when he was
first tutsi device and experience his own design
and was really kind of it was magical moment for him it was while.
This is my at my work and it's almost physical already so it was a great
feedback.
Anyone else.
Sure, I can tell a little bit of a story that we I came
as a second wave of people from my university the first wave came
and they're in the process of planning a new health education campus
where we're taking people from medicine nursing and dentistry and social work and all
these different professional fields and we were building a building.
That was meant to be to provide the
future of our field of medicine for the next fifty-year hundred-years.
they came and they saw this technology and they came home and they said mark you need to go
and I had no idea what I was expecting to see nothing.
But, yet when we put that the whole
...on for the first-time my entire world changed and I
...has anybody done the hollow lens academy here does anybody
I was anybody's world not changed by that experience I'd like to
meet you because this is just it completely...to how
minefield is going to go forward not just educational component but also
the professional component this is going to change every piece of what we do
and I can't think of a technology since
...mri heresy to your and ultrasound thirty years ago that has changed that has a
potential change our fuel that much.
And, the you might think forwards thirty years from now we're going to be
all of us...I it's just an amazing place to
be actually I've kind of a fun story so that's the product that we did is
sky-high we started with the notion
not you have this amazing technology and then so important
...how do we have that... people and specially every everyday people.
So, we really pushed on how do we how do we deliver something around
connecting people in communication and there's all these social laps and things out there but
...like kind of these broadcast things and they're great for the broadcast but
he bring people together so, the first-time we actually
got just kind of an early prototype call working...the device on and I
was like a little mock-up room of some stuff and I was walking around...one of the
...parlors on our team I could hear her right here like she
was just standing next to me and I was pretending look at magazines and do all this stuff and I
was and I was so blown away with what I understood
right in that moment about what we were really going to be able to push forward and you and that
was that was really exciting I felt like she was like really there with
me she was commenting on the things I was looking at she was telling me to go look at something else and
that's...aspired to how do we get further into sort of
that-you interaction and I think one of the things
...as you all think about what you'll create?
In develop is we had a lot of people go I don't know I don't think communication will be good on
this and...
But, there but it you can do amazing things that you didn't think
were possible so you know,
are just like...is imaginative and is and push forward with as many things you can
I'm so truly excited to see what other people will get out and create,
you know,
I know we've only like gotten...scratched the surface in terms of some of the things and there's people out
...so many great ideas soto be it'll be really,
really exciting again in the next,... even five years?
Some arguments in the future...you talk a lot about, you know,
the excitement you have where your field is going...you have any developer experience before working with
...like...through the career before followers so, yeah,
I have a programming background...and what we do in large part in our
world is in my lab in particular is build mri machines so,
these are everything from applied math and physics on one
in through software implementation actual getting it on the scanner working with our partners and
...scanning it on patients in clinical trials we have that whole pathway so, you know,
I'm not because I spend...time in all of...other areas
that's definitely time that's taken away from development used to be,
you know, a few years ago like program pretty well?
But, I if I could speak to the experience so the first-time I sat down.
I knew unity.
At a reasonable level but, I thought I'm going
to be the worst-case scenario for a developer that's going to be sitting down and
programming on this so I started my stopwatch from when I first open
up the sdk to the time when I had my first hologram in front of me
was just a cubicle admit but it was less than five minutes
and that to me was absolutely not what I expected
I expected when we came to the first-time I actually brought the math people
in the people, you know,
I thought we were going to be solving for surfaces and trying to figure out
...triangulation dvs on everything the hard math and there was
none of that it was almost drag-and-drop star
...so within fifteen minutes
or whole mindset of our team switched from doing the
...math work that we do in the lab to my god this is
just content generation at this point there's going to be some you...development
in interface that we have to do but most of the time that we're going to
...spending going forward is just taking data from...
cities the ultrasounds the photographic things and bringing this
the into the hall...environment
you just starting with unity and presenting in a way that people can understand that's
a totally different problem than what I thought I would be working on at this stage?
So, what you said that's one of your most exciting things about developing
problems or if you had to choose something that was most exciting what would it be...putting on for the first-time?
Certainly, certainly...standpoint that that's I mean I am shocked and the
reason that I'm sitting here right now is that reason that this is so ready to go so,
ready to get out into the world in
terms of where it's at all of you who've gone through the holographic academy I was sitting in
there yesterday and I could see the same thing on all of your faces that were
there and if you if you haven't gone through it find somebody who has because these guys
...microsoft have really done a fantastic job of getting this
sophisticated the point where it's going to be a blast when it gets...into the world.
...what about you what...most surprising.
Answer that I don't know...something for me it when you think about it
the digital like your digital like...created like this digital
...the fact that we say digital world like with technology and,
what I realized, you know,
early on ways well there...actually breaking the digital world now
we're bringing the advancement to the real-world so it's like,
you know, in the internet and all these things that often like this paper area here where is
that where does that actually exist right it doesn't feel as, you know,
real...so the opportunity to actually
...all of that into sort of the real-world and contacts
is just it's really exciting because it brings us back to
...more human state I think it allows us even you
can underestimate sometimes I think just being heads up and hands-free and
able the move about your spaces your as your as you're
doing things and that is something that just personally excites me because, you know,
I love technology but I love technology to serve people so,
I think this to me is...core of hitting on that?
Absolutely...human-human, human-human...yeah,
so, if you go back and you think about the things that have all the things that have come in
our digital world since,
you know, cult eighties or whatever everything that has come through has made
our connections to people who are distant much better but it has
absolutely made the connection to the person sitting next to you much worse we'll sit around
at dinner and...phone or I if I'm lecturing at
university in a setting like this probably half the students are looking at a laptop and not
looking at me if I'm in a smaller setting, you know, if...if
...computer screens there maybe you can get two people sitting at a computer together but then there's a
monitor that separates them same thing at work
where all of you guys work I'm sure you can maybe have a connection with one or two people but,
doing anything more than that with the digital world right now is next to
impossible and I can immediately see that you could get twenty people almost
like a museum sitting around a digital object this is the same thing
...we're talking about with architecture example or sitting on mars are
...all of these things that we're talking about actually
serve to increase your human interaction and I can't think of another piece of
digital technology that does that person-to-person like this but that's why I'm here that's fantastic.
Well, I'm actually rolling back slightly to the...surprisewhat surprised me
I've two things that came to my mind immediately the first one which is by far
...the greatest surprise that I had in the term
...working with it has to be the first-time that
...was brought to tears by the experience of standing on
mars and,
at the first item...mention by...the first-time that it happened we were all
shocked and little uncomfortable like we, you know, what
...we do this person steering up...very emotional and, it first we thought okay
it's must be this person, you know, this person is a little maybe
a little bit I've seen it twice I'll tell you...happened twice actually I mean since then it's
happened around eight or nine times that I've witness but it speaks to
something about that...I think we're touching we
...some kind of threshold and access to wish fulfillment that many of us not
every one of us but many of us have of being in a place
...that in many ways feels inaccessible to us
today and that we're working very hard to make accessible in many different ways but
...be suddenly just thrust into that many of them without any warning whatsoever I mean they
were just they showed up and like...the first demo well here's a first demo in
...and they're just, you know, it's...overwhelming moment for
many of them that was it was a big surprise the first-time it happened I didn't
expect that added at all and is since become less of a surprise...happened several times
...time to reflect on that the second surprise for me comes back to sort
of new interaction...a good example of one of these unexpected things that you
would just you'll discover while you're working with the hardware and it was when we
were working on the early days of our ui and part of our system is that we interfaces with
another tool that we use to command the rovers and sometimes we imaginary
...sitting down at a desk when they use it and they would move there
the using the mouse and keyboard on this computer and we know where that is we cut it out of the
augmentation you can see your computer and you can see
...around you and when we were several of us commented...we were working
in wearing the whole and that we kept trying to move the mouse
...off the edge the monitor was just this thing that kept happening to us
relate just that's ridiculous I can't do that can't possibly move your mouse
...out onto the surface of mars that's not going to
work and then suddenly couple of us we're like what if we could do that like what would
that be like and one of the guys on the team the anime...the guy
...microsoft team with that up in the afternoon and we did it
...like a magic moment...was just like while this really,
really works and I think it's something we're using I think you guys
...as well so I cheated...to surprises as my two big ones.
So, ...in our industry where construction...
But, they do share this experience moving the mouse and actually in the proof of concept you can see this in
the movies...moving the mouse of this
...screen this three-d modeling applications screen into the holographic environment and
a funny story we had this movies now and youtube and one of the first
...and your keywords kind it's kind of there's a physical model
...around and...the hologram in the middle and in the movies users actually putting the
mouse on the physical model so the guy who was watching this and youtube demented the am
...putting the mouse on the hologram this is really true
kind of ironically he didn't understand it
couldn't differentiate between the hologram in the middle
and the physical object around so great experience again from the from the
...graphic capability point of view.
...geoff kind of mentioned this before but ...talk about tools and the tools...you use for
developing problems are you able who are you in your team able to use existing tools and kind of integrate into those
are...learn a whole new skillset...to do everything from scratch.
Yeah, so, it's not...I mean organizer using csharp and unity and they could
uses knowledge when developing for haul...
I think again and we mentioned earlier there's a lot of...here and
on the graphic side so having an expert is an artist dev
...is essential for success.
there's other part of this kind of extending so there's one part which is about the technical aspect
...skills...needs and,
there is aspect of our users and what is
read attractive for me in this approach our customers invest quite a lot of
money and time you know, teaching themselves on the existing tool...tools
...pretty complex and takes time to be an expert and what we're doing here is a whole as we're not
...them to replace the existing technology
...telling them we have here technology which can extend your capabilities you can still use your existing
tool but you will be able to do much more you'll be able to experience your
designing much better way and share it with others so for me it's
a great message for the for the market in for our customers?
That's a core part of the
...value proposition for us as well we have in the case
the curiosity rover mission a huge investment in the tools that operate
that spacecraft and was not something that we could or desire to just recap
clearly toss out we didn't have to we found and also
mention by the way that because this is so young this work area
is so new we haven't figured out every thing that it's best for
yet and if we had to suddenly like from the get-go do everything, you know,
replace completely everything we've done before I think it
would have been very hard possibly impossible for us to succeed so what we could do instead was, you know,
what these problems are the ones we think that this technology going to help us
most width and focus on those and then keep the connection back to the original tool
set and continue using it for what it made the most sense for got a lot of questions for-you
...I've got one that came through ...a surface have app and transform it into a...out?
Yes, you can...
...so ...lewinsky type one of the things that we did.
One of the things that we did around
...experiences we actually we wanted to make sure that we could connects to
anybody so there's three hundred-million scape users out there and,
we wanted to make sure that no matter who you wanted to call you
could so we actually unlocked and the ability to
...from a tablet into a hollow lens so you can have interaction from
any device through the holland so even if my mom didn't have a highlands
you she could actually ...sky policy and interact and really rich and,
...way so we think if anybody has...and
...the you ap sessions or any of those kinds of thingslooking really getting involved
in...kind of the whole...ap model that we've released because how
...of...a windows ten device so we're now looking and we've
got some other projects going we're actually playing a little bit back and forth where now take actually
...app that we created on how a lens and then,
you know, put that into the tablet...we have that actually working as well
now too so if you didn't get a chance to see the
...demo I think there's some video of it but hollis studios which is on
...we now have on the tablet as well so really kind of pushing how we can
make that easy-going back and forth we talk about experiences through hollow lens and through like let's say
a tablet how do you share experiences across multiple...users...is for any of you.
Well, we add why don't we haven't announced...we're going to...
you can so obviously I mean where your sky so we have ability to call another
...user and we have a pretty cool experience that will hopefully be showing
in the next coming months around how you can actually interact with other hollow
...users where you get to short of share my view and I get and then
I can turn around and see someone else's view so when you think about collaboration and,
especially like remote workplaces for collaboration like this becomes really powerful
opportunity and to work around...around that but it is possible this?
I can hit...here that again, in the construction is...very common you could that
you would find architect in long dong the structure engineering seattle
and the project is in denver colorado and in this kind of
semi you must have an efficient collaboration process and there is there are some
tools to collaborate and...all base today on these kind of
tutti screen or three-d model behind...to the screen and what
we experienced in the last few weeks is ability to collaborate with
the hologram so I can be somewhere in the world collaboratively seminars
will both see the hologram
...each one of us from the point of view he's tending but you also see the position
and the gaze of the other users which means I know what
are talking about and this is a fantastic collaboration technology?
from the beginning we knew that...mars application had to support collaboration
because mission control mission operations is this inherently collaborative tasks are
science team is spread around the world and many of them are first and
foremost something else they might be university professor they might be...research lab in
their participating in this mission in a small slice of their time so what we
want to do I mean it sounds just ridiculous impossible until we did is that
we wanted to make it possible for them in that like fifteen minutes slot that they needed to like contribute
to a decision to stand on mars beside the other members of the team and
say here's what I think and here's what
we come over here and have a look at this from this angle and if we take it for granted
how important physical
...presence is in decision-making especially
...something physical like architecture like or like expiration and,
I think about education too...
it shouldn't be overlooked and that's what we access with that now one thing we haven't yet done with
on-site is make it so that multiple people in the same room can experience
marge together...for actually physically in the same room...by the way that have to expel that
also careful a but anyway if within the same room really and together and,
we want to both see...it's something we see a clear path for how we how we
could do that it was not the case we focused on first because most of our scientists are not in
the same room together but it's something I think we will ultimately do so for me
the point I wanted head-on was to go back to the open challenges
their the to meet gets back to this user interface to indicate the
we're people are standing or what they're looking at
...to on-site demo it's the same on the videos
...real-life is great indicating that you can see a
model there's a cursor that shows where the person's looking at you can see
...right there what where they're headers pointed but this
is relatively simple at this point I would argue and I think the this
is the next big challenge in interaction spaces what how is that
...look when we get further along how do you control
...we have a model in front of...model in front
of a group of people how you control who's interacting with it
...at a given time how do you move that control back and forth these
are these are open questions and again it's this I think we're going to start with something that looks
very much like a computer today but I don't imagine ending their role?
...to actually tell us a little bit more values in
...educational setting what advantages dc that it presents
...current technology well as I said earlier I think that it's the kind of thing that you could bring
people together in the same room looking at something digital the thing so
...talk about medicine a lot but,
to me actually the thing that I think about first is actually my son
he's twelve and he's...
About roman
...right now and you have this problem of
younger you've got a twelve-year-old learning about some people who died two thousand
years ago from little thumbnail pictures in a book.
And, there's just no way that you can make that exciting
...I really, you know, I love my...social studies teacher
...history teachers because of that fact and yet with just
a very simple set of digital assets you could bring a
since you're in here and boom there in front of view or bring a you know,
a model of
...and drop it in front of...and these are the kinds of
things that you just can't do any other way so we could do it
on a computer screen it's still you don't see the since you're in real size
in you can't walk around them and talk about their arm or whatever and that's
a kind of thing that even if you just had a model of us ensuring sitting there.
Just the first day of class I think everybody would immediately connect
with that material and you can go back to the book and learn from the book and have some sort of context?
But, otherwise you just you just don't have that engagement
and this is almost easy at this point all you gotta do is work-up,
you know, this problem of getting twenty
how lenses on the same time and being able to buy them and being able to.
Over...the but it all of us wanted sorry.
But, you know, that...that moment if you do that first day of class
...that first day the chapter you've completely changed the
person's mind that kids mine for the rest of the class.
And, they will be open to learning that material in a
way that it's just not possible today you could do it in history you can do to
...can do it in computer science you can do anywhere and that dot I don't know-how
...do that that's the revolutionizing
...like to add a note about education process actually.
Architects
also to educate themselves on what you're doing all the time to in design process and
...some unique feature in this technology which is really
...also and educational...ability to move between.
This kind of line reality to richard t so when you're in a class you
don't want to immersive yourself completely in a typical scenario you don't want to the
...experience a completely virtual world you need to see
the teacher notices other people around you and actually.
You're going to do it in kind...mixed reality environment but.
In some cases back to the architecture practice I would like to immerse myself in the design I
would like to understand how people industry to experience...building
...is a great way to be able to actually move along this mine from
...oddity to the real
...and decide where I want to be along this line
...making decisions so
what type of challenges that does that give you when it comes to designing ui and augmented reality?
Yeah, that's again brings easy the question how to provide
the control to our users in kind of easy way I mean how
not too much you...which will interfere between him and the
read environment on the other hand how to...the flexibility to control what he's
...exploring multiple ways to do it including putting the new front of the
user putting...specific locations environment...even using,
you know, some accessories to control the environment's all
these is optional and you guys should decide what is best in your specific project.
Just commenting on new it's already
...refrain in this talk unsurprisingly and this is this.
Is very focused on the user experience is a big part of you know,
where the new grounds broken here so the with onsite, you know,
we went through a lot of revisions early on about trying to figure out how do you blend the need
to have controls and the needs to also have as an obstructed of
the experience of being on mars as possible you know,
one thing that just getting specific on a couple things that
we've learned like when I...my mention that I had the initial imprint ideals like you know,
maybe I want some of the cy kind of like a heads up display sort of like focused in my
field of view but sort of like up kind of moving with my head as if it were on a
pane of glass...from my face and, you know, it seems like a good idea of the...I
...experience has been that isn't at least from my experience the best way to do...instead moved
the ui elements out into the world out into the virtual world
...you interact with film not as if they were entirely physical
...they behave in ways that are a little bit more free the
normal physical object and use cascading and things like that
but that made it much more rooted in the environment it kept us
in our users in that martian environment while they were interacting with some of these
...controls and then we went through a lot of revisions about well, you know,
things like should...shadows on march,
you know,...pluses and minuses to the to that you know,
if you cast a shadow it could obscures something but shadows make this object feel more
rooted in more something like I can interact that naturally so these are
just a sampling really of some of the things we've learned
vertex sharing more of what we've learned with all...you and then descriptions I hope, you know,
getting some help from you guys about things you're learning to?
So, people...got a chance...well, I mean I guess if you've been to academy and start learning
...how would you say since people cannot buy...they get started...these people
...get ready ok so first I'll tell you is the number one question I get from my daughter
every day sarah by mom is
...available when can I get it can I get one or you bring home and how much is going to be
mom she text view this...very precocious and excited so,
we are you know, the best way to stay on top of the latest information that we're going to share is make sure
you're part of the windows insider program and you can obviously always go to
...microsoft highlands dot com as well and
were not sharing a lot of that information just yet but, you know,
there will be more information coming out and sort of the next
you period of time...
Success
...on the soon trained...talk about sdk availability www.
...again, windows insider program will be where
will be announcing information related that we know that everybody is really
excited...anxious to get we are excited anxious to share that and, you know,
windows insider program will be the best place to get the first
availability information about outside of anywhere else.
On the topic of like how to be prepared for
...developing for this I think the skill set that I feel overlaps well with this
of course we've said many times...is new this is...is into an exact match
and skillset but mobile three-d application development is a place
...you have skills in that area you're going to I think get some real transfer
...of skills if you don't a place where you might want to do some
experimentation by...it's fun area too I think you
...the that I think it will introduce you to the thinking
about space in a slightly different way of thinking about interaction in a slightly different way.
Can I add to that we haven't really touched on the audio part of
the experience I think this three-dimensional audio response of
the device is one of the key things that makes
it seem real so for those of you who work in audio space that's something that will be immensely
valuable here also the voice commands I think that's a key part of
the user experience this is another shocking thing, you know,
I I've had some students working on the sdk and,
they tried to break it...we have...universal holographic commanders do this
thing because you can you can look at something that's supposed to do something if you don't want to
...tap you can just say do thing and that takes care of...jorge...
...knows what you're looking at but, you know,
we've done crazy commands like ptwo and things like this and they all work so,
that kind of thinking...said earlier you've got your
hands-free and there's going to be times when imagine a surgeon has this thing
on their scoping to the to the person...continent who's giving them the
advice that's all going to happen through voice and the iii audio so that you stay in touch
with your environment is going to be key so that that's something that I think would be valuable?
Yeah, I think audio I'm also looking at technical...you know,
we have actually have with a mix of people from sort of like traditional kind of engineering and game
engineering and I kind of learned over time that was like a really good blend of people so
you have a lot of good skill transfer kinda going back and forth is people helped each other you
...different things in different areas you know,
so, I think, you know, kind of looking...sort of some of those disciplines and...and figuring out I convex
...that was that was something we definitely figured out over time as a good recipe...going to add,
... on your eyes funny cause I was what's really cool about what we can do is that
you can break apart the dui you can make
it and pieces and you can put this thing here and you can there's a lot of flexibility to it so
...the experiences that you need to deliver whatever the user like really needs to do there
is a tremendous amount of ways that you can actually solve that problem which also makes it hard...lot of ways
...to solve it and mixing it but the ability to use your voice and,
...here where something might be so even if like at one point we had we
did we put we put a menu over there and then you turn around you're like wait where
I put the menu right and then but if you actually with the
spatial audio you-can, you-can here where
a hologram is over here and, then you can also use voice to just call it back to you so,
there's a lot of great things around that or even just with gesture and I
could say well actually I want the smaller maybe I want bigger or, you know,
maybe I just want to put it over here so you're actually giving the user the flexibility sort
of organized the way that will make the most sense for them...so I think
that was something that we really learned and we definitely wanted to ensure that,
you know, people who
were still participating in the real-world so they could do that and,
not have a bunch of stuff all in their face and getting in the way because they're really trying to achieve something
here right now and, then again all these things are just about helping them get that thing, you know,
sort of done whether it's having a great conversation are doing surgery or?
I just will quickly added that I think that's the key thing that they're invent showed
at the keynote was that you can take that information that you
want and put it where you want and
its own absolutely natural to be able to have your email
...your sky over here and inhabit where you want I don't we don't do that today we have
all monitor we have of phone...we have watch and,...always has to be
...that abilities is going to be fantastic to see work goes.
So, you talk about different rooms and different use cases how do you test for
all the different variables that are out there are there any tools are built-in that allow you to do that right back to make
...a diagonal the hard ones get actually this is a goods so, the a lot of
...so what we do a lot of testing and one of the things
at with our designers as,
you know, we come up with like a hundred scenarios and,
then we actually had them...sort of many stations
and go-round and try to do all...so...say yes we could do
...we defuse a bomb and we at one point we actually we had like a little loop bombs
...like could we, you know, could we do it and,
this is where it's also interesting right because now we're actually testing the technology in the real-world
because we can just apply it right there and see you know-how it how it's working so drawing we
can be teacher draw yes we can teacher drawn so we're just able to go through very quickly and
kind of iterate on things are working and then learn what was happening with the tools that we
are creating very quickly as well so you know, we could go back and go wait, you know,
this line doesn't actually work here on
this surface and maybe this is something different we need to go back and think about how do we tool that well
when we put the...this way it doesn't actually line-up so then we go back and we kind of
...tool that we spend a lot of time in scenario testing because we
...so on the topic of your testing for different environments where we're now moving into the phase where
we're sort of turning beta
testing of the system with our scientists and that means?
Learning about the environment's that they're going to use it in it's, you know,
sort of like the science-fiction part of our brain, you know,
probably imagines like it's going to be like this vast empty room with like yellow grid
on black floors something like that that's not how they work that's not...the work environments look like I mean
they're in offices are in cubicles and...get stuff all of their desk they've got,
you know, quart across the floor and things like that and, you know, we didn't want
...we set on this project we didn't want to build a system that they had to
go to we didn't want them to have to like well, that's in the in building nine hundred twenty and I
...walk down the street and get my car and drive to that building if I want this experience
wanted it right where they were so we're dealing with now is
like okay well how do we support the diversity of the work
...that they have if you recall...of our
...application is that it knows where their computer is it cuts out
there computer from the martian environment that come up with ways to address the fact
that turns out most people's offices are slightly smaller than the planet mars
so we had to figure out like how could they move on mars
...only naturally within the...office within beyond the walls of their office and,
that's taken a lot of learning, you know, we go out we try things and
discover that wowed you should have seen this guy's office, you know, who's
in it so we gotta think about that...think about what his office is going to be like when he's using it so,
we're learning that...rate as we speak I have to ask just for selfish reasons,
you know, the response to
...has been ridiculously positive I think people are excited about it is
that an experience that's going to become publicly available so nasa's.
Focus...always been to explore...share and we
...for me personally and, for my team we have every intention
of finding a way to share this experience with everyone I would almost feel it
responsible not too so we are right now is that we don't have you don't have
the specifics...we don't have enough...to make but there's just
a of fiery passion within my team to see that
happened so early hope to...something about...future.
Suggest touchdown...talking about mars
...office space how important is working with scale with what you do with your experience so
...architecture scale is almost about everything I need to understand how my design
is related to the environment it might be city scape or
interior design in any case I must be aware to the scale of
my designed compared to what is around me and paul...is doing a great job
induce again bringing that data into the real-world the ability to compare
and to see how I can interact...design is a great experience
...is one slide this at ranch of technology I must say and
...the early days we met with one of the most influential
architects in the world today and I cannot specify names but after
...so that demo it was looking at...and I was a bit
...consent already about what is going to send the first version hasek is connect...
it and unfortunately not exist point and I'm really waiting for the
...for the day I can actually touchy movie squeeze it and
...to pieces and...to be a great way to experience designing
...for obvious since we only have a few minutes left
is there anything you'd like to wrap up with anything that you'd like to say you feel the room should now?
Leave it up to each of you.
And, your stumps now.
I averages say you know, to me it's a it's a paradigm shift, you know,
this is also been it's been along it's a hard journey in some in many cases like pushing
against something can be really like this can be really tough like you get a breakthrough
and it's like my god the most amazing euphoria and then you run into problems
...that you sticking with that the opportunity I think we
all have where I'm where this takes is just enormous sentence enormous for all kinds of
people for businesses for users for my daughter I see, you know,
so, much opportune whether it's where how she wants to play in different ways
or learn in new ways because she can now understand complex systems because she just experiences
them so it's just been great to have everybody's really positive
response so maybe my last comment which is a lot of words before that is just thank you.
Of...a-c things also to the microsoft folks...this together because I think it's a rare
...are standing at a rare moment where things are going to change based on
this technology and I, you know,
there's very few of those things that you can get close to in someone's life
and I feel just incredibly fortunate to be a part of this and I really as I
said on wednesday I can't wait to see what you guys are going to do with this because we, you know,
it's a relatively small team compared to the rest of world that
has developed this and I just can't wait to see where we go from here.
For me the toughest task now is
to manage customer expectations I mean after the demo...proof of concept
because so many request to participate and to start working with the devised
and, I would encourage all of you...start explore it's amazing technology.
Well, I'll shameless...mention that we're looking to hire technical
artist but, btwo you...
But, no, in...also had that I want to...would ...about the.
The rarity of events like this and
adam not referring to this conference I mean a moment where these
technologies come together in a moment that new things become possible and I
...of incredibly privilege to be a part of that but what I'm really looking
forward to is that even up here on stage you see these very disparate
applications I mean you have medicine you have architecture in space exploration but,
really so many similarities as well so part of what's wonderful about development and
about the things that we build is that there are far more similarities once you
get one-inch below sort of the domain then there are differences and
I looking for to benefiting from all of that as a larger community...
All right well that's going to do it for us I believe jeff and mark or available to stick around
outside for questions meagan has to take off and catch a plane that she's already late for an ob
yet has a meeting thank you guys so much for joining us today we really do appreciate have a great.